Guide to the Daniel S. and Jane Balderston Dye Papers
Yale University Divinity School Library
Daniel S. and Jane Balderston Dye Papers
1905-1987
RG 22
Yale University Divinity School Library
8
(19 boxes + 1 oversize portfolio)
Substantive letters refer to the social and political scene in the Chengtu area, as well as providing a thorough account of the educational mission work of the Dyes at West China Union University. The papers include unique documentation of patterns and designs used in West China latticework, woven belts, and pottery. Drawings of hundreds of patterns and notes regarding their origin and symbolism are included. Daniel Sheets Dye taught academic courses at West China Union University in Chengtu, Szechuan Province, from 1910 to 1949, serving under the American Baptist Foreign Missionary Society. As an avocation Dye recorded and analyzed window lattice and woven belt patterns, which often had swastika designs, throughout West China. Jane Balderston went to West China in 1915, serving under the Friends Foreign Mission Association of Great Britain and Ireland. After her marriage to Daniel Dye in 191, she taught mathematics and education courses at Woman's Normal School in Chengtu and West China Union University Normal School.
Dye, Daniel Sheets, 1888-
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Nancy Balderston Conrad and Herbert E. Sloan, 1990. Addendum gift of estate of J. Calvin Bright, 1999.
Conditions Governing Access
Open to qualified researchers.
Biographical / Historical
1884 Feb Daniel Sheets Dye born in Ohio.
1886 Apr Jane Canby Balderston born in Maryland.
1907 DSD graduated from Denison University, Phi Beta Kappa.
1908 JBD graduated from Wellesley College.
1908 DSD went to Szechuan, West China to study Chinese in preparation for teaching science at West China Union University.
1908-1915 JBD taught at secondary schools in Ohio and Pennsylvania.
1910-1949 DSD taught at West China Union University, serving under American Baptist Foreign Missionary Society. As an avocation, DSD recorded and analyzed window lattice and woven belt patterns, which often had swastika designs, throughout West China. DSD was a founder of the West China Border Research Society and of the West China Union University museum.
1915 JBD went to West China under the auspices of the Friends Foreign Mission Association of Great Britain and Ireland; taught at Szechuan Boarding School in Tungchwan.
1919 DSD and JBD married. Under the auspices of the American Baptist Foreign Missionary Society, JBD taught mathematics and education at Woman's Normal School in Chengtu and West China Union University Normal School. JBD became an expert on birds of West China.
Study during furloughs in the United States led to an M.A. from Cornell University for DSD and an M.A. from Columbia University for JBD.
1937 Two volume work by DSD entitled A Grammar of Chinese Lattice published by Harvard University Press.
1940 DSD received honorary doctorate from Denison University.
1949 Returned to Colora, Maryland following Communist takeover in China.
1950-1960 Served as co-directors of John Woolman Memorial in Mt. Holly, New Jersey prior to retirement in Colora. JBD instrumental in organizing North East Maryland branch of the Women's International League for Peace and Freedom.
1976 JBD died in Colora, Maryland.
1977 DSD died in Colora, Maryland.
Scope and Contents
I. Correspondence, 1908-1987.
II. Writings and Notes, 1907-1977.
III. Personal Items and Memorabilia, 1905-1977, n.d.
IV. Addendum
These papers provide valuable documentation regarding West China. Substantive letters refer to the social and political scene in the Chengtu area, as well as providing biographical information regarding the Dyes and a thorough account of their educational mission work at West China Union University. These papers complement in a useful way the official files of West China Union University found in YDSL Record Group No. 11, Archives of the United Board for Christian Higher Education in Asia. Daniel Dye was also a friend and colleague of Thomas Torrance, whose papers are available in YDSL Record Group No. 16.
The papers include unique documentation of patterns and designs used in West China latticework, woven belts, and pottery. Drawings of hundreds of different patterns recorded by Dye and his artistic assistants are available in the collection. Dye spent many years in analyzing the origins and symbolism of the patterns which he collected. He was unable to complete the scholarly work which he hoped to produce on this subject, but his explanations and theories are available for appraisal in myriad drafts.
The Dye Papers are also valuable for the thorough documentation they provide regarding the life of a successful woman missionary. Jane Balderston Dye, married but childless, found herself in ideal circumstances to be effective in a university teaching career, to travel broadly, to assist her husband in his scholarly pursuits, and to pursue her own avocation of the study of birds in West China.
The correspondence in Series I consists primarily of letters written by Dan and Jane Dye to their families in the United States. For many years they wrote long, descriptive letters to their "home folks" every week. Beginning shortly before their marriage in 1919, Dan and Jane alternated weeks writing to both families. The correspondence becomes less frequent and more condensed during the 1930s and 1940s. During the early part of 1927, Jane was evacuated to Shanghai due to political unrest in West China. The months of separation, before Dan joined her in Shanghai, provide the only correspondence between Jane and Dan (1927 Feb-Apr.)
Series II consists of published writings by Dan and Jane Dye, unpublished essays by Dan, and extensive notes and reflective drafts by Dan for his anticipated work Swastica Sinica: The Pattern of Patterns of the Far East. These notes and drafts were written primarily during the period from Dan's retirement in 1950 until his death in 1977. Eleanor Hough wrote in her biographical memoir about Dan: "We know that DSD found writing very difficult, hence the dozens and dozens of repetitions of the same material. The fact that he never seemed to arrive at a satisfactory and complete statement of any of the segments of his research was a combination of advancing years and his realization that his conclusions might be denounced by those he admired and respected." The categories used to organize the notes and drafts follow the arrangement made prior to their donation to the Divinity Library. The drawings of designs included in this Series represent hours of painstaking effort to accurately record the lattice and belt designs discovered by Dye during his travels throughout West China and Tibet. The drawings have been transferred from their original folders into acid-free folders, and any notations on the old folders have been transferred to the new. There does not seem to be any particular order to or classification of the designs.
Series III, Personal Items and Memorabilia, includes biographical documentation regarding the Dyes, and an interesting collection of photographs and slides. The photographs and slides provide valuable illustration of Western missionaries in West China and of the costumes, artwork, architecture, and landscapes of West China.
The Addendum represented by Series IV was received from the estate of J. Calvin Bright, a colleague of the Dyes in West China. It includes correspondence and writings of Daniel and Jane Balderston Dye that are very similar to the materials in Series I and II. It is not clear why these materials were in the possession of Bright.
Arrangement
I. Correspondence, 1908-1987
II. Writings and Notes, 1907-1977
III. Personal Items and Memorabilia, 1905-1977, n.d.
IV. Addendum
Art -- China -- Szechuan Province; Education -- China; Minorities -- China; Missions -- China; Swastikas in art; Women missionaries; Educators; Missionaries; Dye, Daniel Sheets, 1888-; Dye, Jane Balderston, 1886-1976; Hua xi xie he da xue
- Correspondence, 1908-1987; Series I
  - Family Correspondence
    - Daniel Dye to family
      - on board ship and journey to West China, 1908 Oct-Dec (Box 1, Folder 1)
      - primarily from Suifu and Chengtu, 1909 - 1911 (Box 1, Folder 2 - 6)
      - from Shanghai, Jan-Aug, 1912 Jan-Aug (Box 1, Folder 7)
      - from Ichang to Chengtu, 1912 Aug-Dec (Box 1, Folder 7)
      - primarily from Chengtu, 1913 (Box 1, Folder 8)
      - journey home for furlough, 1914 Feb-Apr (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - Jane Balderston to family
      - on board ship to China, 1915 Oct-Dec (Box 1, Folder 10)
      - journey from Shanghai to Chungking, 1916 Jan-Mar (Box 1, Folder 11)
      - from Friends Mission, Chengtu, 1916 Apr-Jun (Box 1, Folder 12)
      - from Friends Mission, Chengtu, 1916 Jul-Dec (Box 2, Folder 13-14)
      - primarily from Tungchwan, 1917 - 1918 (Box 2, Folder 15-20)
    - DSD and JBD to families in U.S.
      - from Chengtu, 1918 Apr-Dec (Box 2, Folder 21)
      - primarily from Chengtu, 1919 - 1922 (Box 2, Folder 22-27)
      - from Chengtu, journey home, NYC, 1923 (Box 3, Folder 28)
      - in U.S. and return to West China, 1924 (Box 3, Folder 29)
      - from Chengtu, 1926 - 1927 Mar (Box 3, Folder 30-31)
      - from Chengtu; JBD from Shanghai after 3/27; DSD from Shanghai after 5/27; return to W. China 8/27, 1927 Apr-Dec (Box 3, Folder 32-34)
      - from Chengtu; journey home via Europe, 1928 - 1932 Jul (Box 3, Folder 35-39)
      - from Chengtu (11 letters), 1934 - 1936 (Box 3, Folder 40-42)
      - primarily from Chengtu, 1937 - 1938 (Box 3, Folder 43-44)
      - from Chengtu; journey home, 1939 - 1940 Jul (Box 4, Folder 45-47)
      - in U.S.; return voyage to China, 1941 May-Nov (Box 4, Folder 48)
      - primarily from Chengtu, 1942 - 1948 Oct (Box 4, Folder 49-55)
    - Jane Balderston Dye to Daniel Dye
      - JBD (in Shanghai) to DSD (in W. China), 1927 Feb-Apr (Box 4, Folder 56)
  - General Correspondence
    - Correspondence of DSD and JBD with others
      - "circular letters" from DSD and JBD, 1925 - 1931 (Box 4, Folder 57)
      - to/from DSD; incl. DSD annual letter to Mission Board (1918), letter re. proposed cooperation between WCUU and the American Museum of Natural History of New York (1938), and letter from Thomas Torrance (1941), 1909-1941 (Box 4, Folder 58)
      - to/from DSD; incl. to/from Calvin Bright, 1949 - 1977, n.d. (Box 4, Folder 59)
      - to/from JBD; incl. from Henry T. Hodgkin, 1917 - 1938 (Box 4, Folder 60)
    - Correspondence not with DSD or JBD
      - to Jane's mother from Margaret Impey, 1918 (Box 4, Folder 61)
      - to Eleanor Dye re. publication of book by DSD, 1937
      - from American Baptist Foreign Mission Society to families of DSD and JBD, 1924 - 1942 (Box 4, Folder 62)
      - general letters from H. J. Openshaw and R. J. Davidson, 1911, 1918 (Box 4, Folder 63)
      - Calvin Bright to Nancy Balderston Conrad and Eleanor Hough, 1977 - 1982 (Box 4, Folder 64)
      - to/from Nancy Balderston Conrad and Eleanor Hough, 1977 - 1987 (Box 4, Folder 65)
- Writings and Notes, 1907-1977; Series II; 7 boxes (3 linear feet)
  - Writings of DSD
    - Early writings at Denison University (typescript), ca. 1907 (Box 5, Folder 66)
    - "Some Ancient Circles, Squares, Angles and Curves in Earth and in Stone in Szechuan, China" Journal of the West China Border Research Society, Vol. IV, 1930-1931 (Box 5, Folder 67)
    - "Some Elements of Chinese Architecture with Notes on Szechuan Specialities" Journal `of the West China Border Research Society, (Vol. III?), 1930-1931 (Box 5, Folder 68)
    - "A Study of Chinese Lattice (as of 1899)" Journal of the West China Border Research Society, Vol. IV
    - "The Chengtu Clays- Deposits of Possible Loessial Origin in Western and Northwestern Szechuan Basin" (co-authored with James Thorp) Bulletin of the Geological Society of China, Vol. XV, No.2, 1936 (Box 5, Folder 69)
    - "Sundry Tests upon Five Samples of the Glass Beads" Journal of the West China Border Research Society, 1943
    - "The Yin-Yang Dance of Life and Basic Patterns: as seen in West China between December 1908 and April 1949" (typescript), 1950 (Box 5, Folder 70)
    - "Some Notes on the Sketch Map by J. Huston Edgar of the West China Border" Journal of the West China Border Research Society, n.d. (Box 5, Folder 71)
    - "Chiang Belt Patterns: Tribal Designs from the Sino-Tibetan Border" (typescript)
    - "Man's Discovery of the Immensities" (typescript)
    - "Chinese Lattice with Examples from Szechuan" (typescript)
  - Writings of JBD
    - "Agriculture in West China" The Friend, 1916 (Box 5, Folder 72)
    - "Summering with the Birds at Meng Ting and Omei" Journal of the West China Border Research Society, Vol. XVI, 1946 (Box 5, Folder 73)
    - "Bird Watching 1916-1949 in Chengtu, Szechuan, West China" The Chung Chi Journal, Vol 9, 1969 (Box 5, Folder 74)
  - Lectures of DSD
    - "The Modern Conception of the Universe", 1935 (Box 6, Folder 75)
    - "The Modern Conception of Matter"
    - "The Vital in Chinese Art and the Flowering of Pattern in 18th Century Chengtu", 1956 (Box 6, Folder 76)
  - Notes/drafts of DSD
    - re. Kansu mortuary urns, 1948 - 1977 (Box 6, Folder 77,78)
    - re. Pa Kua, 1950 - 1971 (Box 6, Folder 79-81)
    - re. Pattern symbolism, 1949 - 1962 (Box 7, Folder 82-84)
    - re. Early history of West China, Ch'iang people, I-Ching, etc., 1952 -1975 (Box 7, Folder 85)
    - re. Swastica symbolism in Chinese lattice designs and woven belt designs: myriad drafts and notes related to DSD's proposed book Swastica Sinica: The Pattern of Patterns in the Far East (see boxes for more specific folder labels), 1948 -1977, n.d. (Box 8)
    - re. Swastica symbolism in Chinese lattice designs and woven belt designs: myriad drafts and notes related to DSD's proposed book Swastica Sinica: The Pattern of Patterns in the Far East (see boxes for more specific folder labels), 1948 -1977, n.d. A (Box 9)
    - re. West China belt patterns, 1943 -1954 (Box 9, Folder 100-101)
    - "Analysis of Chinese dictionaries according to frequency of use of radicals in the makeup of characters", n.d. (Box 9, Folder 102)
  - Illustrations of designs
    - in folders (see also oversize portfolio) (Box 10)
    - in folders (Box 11)
    - in rolls (Box 11, Folder 130)
- Personal Items and Memorabilia, 1905-1977, n. d.; Series III; 3 boxes (1 linear foot)
  - Biographical documentation
    - Biographical sketches of DSD and JBD by Dean Kirkwood, Nancy Balderston Conrad and Lloyd Balderston III; newspaper article re. JBD, 1971,1976,1977 (Box 12, Folder 131)
    - Memoir re. DSD written by Eleanor Hough; includes overview of his research on Chinese patterns (2 copies), n.d. (Box 12, Folder 132)
    - DSD: at Denison University, 1905 - 1907 (Box 12, Folder 133)
    - DSD: honorary Doctor of Science from Denison University, 1940 (Box 12, Folder 134)
    - DSD: incl. notices of first departure as missionary, review of A Grammar of Chinese Lattice, 1908-1938 (Box 12, Folder 135)
    - JBD: announcement of marriage to DSD; materials re. "Proposed Woman's College for West China" for which JBD was on Committee of Promotion, notice of Certificate of Honour of the Second Class granted by Government of China, 1919,1921,1941 (Box 12, Folder 136)
    - DSD and JBD: collected documentation of events in West China:- (Box 12, Folder 137)
    - Memorial service for King Edward VII, 1910
    - "Chengtu Siege - Conference", 1911
    - News bulletin from Central China Famine Relief Committee, Shanghai, 1912
    - Reprint from The West China Missionary News :"Shot and Shell; Events in Chengtu during July, 1917"
    - Mimeograph letter to members of mission, 1927
    - 1930 Annual Report, Chengtu, West China by H. J. Openshaw
    - DSD and JBD: U. S. and Chinese passports and visas, 1909 - 1923 (Box OV-d2)
    - Certificate of Honour from Chinese Gov't (JBD), 1940
    - DSD and JBD: U.S. passports and visas, 1922 - 1949 (Box 12, Folder 138)
  - Photographs
    - Portraits
      - DSD, 1906,1908, n.d. (Box 12, Folder 139)
      - JBD, 1908 - 1969 (Box 12, Folder 140)
      - Others: incl. Joseph Beech, Beulah Bonett, Lewis Walmsley, unidentified Chinese individuals (Box 12, Folder 141)
    - Group photos:
      - DSD and JBD / incl. with other missionaries, Chinese individuals, 1919, n.d. (Box 12, Folder 142)
      - DSD with others, ca.1907 - 1924, n.d. (Box 12, Folder 143)
      - JBD with others, 1908. n.d. (Box 12, Folder 144)
      - Gathering of family and friends at Colora, MD, 1969 (Box 12, Folder 145)
      - Chinese individuals; incl. Generalissimo and Mme. Chiang Kai-shek (1935), headdresses, costumes worn by Miao and other border peoples, elementary school classroom scene, etc., 1908 - 1935, n.d. (Box 13, Folder 146)
      - Western individuals, primarily missionaries; incl. "oldest missionaries in Chengtu -1939" (Manly, Torrance, Hartwell, Hutson, etc.), 1909 - 1939, n.d. (Box 13, Folder 147)
    - Buildings/ places/ things:
      - Landscapes, agriculture, ca. 1912 (Box 13, Folder 148)
      - Photo collage assembled by DSD; scenes in West China, with captions, 1917 (Box 13, Folder 149, 150)
      - Design exhibit, n.d. (Box 13, Folder 151)
      - Lattice architecture, n.d. (Box 13, Folder 152-156)
      - Miscellaneous, n.d. (Box 13, Folder 157, 158)
  - Slides:
    - 35 mm. slides divided into following categories- embroidery; carvings; Kansu patterns; vases; carved panels; mortuary urn drawings; weaving; costumes; people; altar set-ups; puppet theater; miscellaneous (Box 14, Folder 159)
- Addendum, Series IV
  - Correspondence
    - Family Correspondence
      - JB to Family, 1906-1914 (Box 15, Folder 160)
      - JB to Family, 1915-1919 (Box 15, Folder 161)
      - DS to Family, 1916-1918 (Box 15, Folder 162)
      - From Chengtu, 1919-1922 (Box 15, Folder 163)
      - On trip to USA, 1923-1924 (Box 15, Folder 164)
      - From Chengtu, 1925-1927 (Box 15, Folder 165)
      - From Chengtu and Shanghai, 1928-1931 (Box 15, Folder 166)
      - On trip to USA via Europe, 1932-1933 (Box 15, Folder 167)
      - From Chengtu, 1933-1936 (Box 15, Folder 168)
      - From Chengtu, 1937-1938 (Box 15, Folder 169)
      - From Chengtu, 1939 (Box 15, Folder 170)
      - On trip to USA, 1940-1941 (Box 16, Folder 171)
      - From Chengtu, 1942-1944 (Box 16, Folder 172)
      - From Chengtu, 1945-1947 (Box 16, Folder 173)
      - From Chengtu, 1948-1949 (Box 16, Folder 174)
      - JB to family, undated (Box 16, Folder 175)
      - Letters between DSD and JB, 1917-1919 (Box 16, Folder 176)
      - DSD to JBD Chengtu to Shanghai, 1927 (Box 16, Folder 177)
    - General Correspondence
      - Circular Letters, 1920-1933 (Box 16, Folder 178)
      - Circular Letters, 1935-1976 (Box 16, Folder 179)
      - Between DSD and Asia Magazine, 1927-1936 (Box 16, Folder 180)
      - Between DSD and others, 1922-1934 (Box 16, Folder 181)
      - Between DSD and others, 1935-1975 (Box 16, Folder 182)
      - Between JBD and others, 1935-1948 (Box 16, Folder 183)
      - Between others regarding DSD (Box 16, Folder 184)
      - Annual reports and Emergency Bulletins from ABFMS, 1929-1942 (Box 17, Folder 185)
      - Letters and Papers re: West China Union University (Box 17, Folder 186)
  - Writings and Notes
    - Writings of Daniel Sheets Dye
      - "Mathematics and Mathematicians", undated (Box 17, Folder 187)
      - "Dynamic Science and Religion", undated
      - "Ink Pictures of the Orthodox Spirit", undated
      - "Puppets from China", undated
    - Writings of Jane Balderston Dye
      - re: Mass Education in China, undated (Box 17, Folder 188)
    - Lectures of Daniel Sheets Dye
      - "Stone Pillows and Heavenly Visitants", 1930 (Box 17, Folder 189)
      - "Dynamics and God", 1930 (Box 17, Folder 189)
      - "Jesus and Our New Universe", 1934 (Box 17, Folder 189)
      - "Immortality", 1935 (Box 17, Folder 190)
      - "Modern Scientists and Religion", 1939 (Box 17, Folder 190)
      - "God and Wonder", 1944 (Box 17, Folder 190)
      - "Creation and the Imminence of God", 1948 (Box 17, Folder 190)
    - Notes/Drafts of DSD
      - re. Science and Religion (Box 17, Folder 191)
      - re. Lattice work (Box 17, Folder 192)
      - re. Biblical Studies (Box 17, Folder 193)
      - re. China - general and misc. (Box 17, Folder 194)
  - Personal items and Memorabilia
    - Biographical Documentation, DSD; Autobiography and ABFMS Questionnaire (Box 17, Folder 195)
    - Biographical Documentation, JBD; incl. speaking engagements, newspaper articles, obituary, family reunion announcement, wedding announcement, picture of first home (Box 17, Folder 196)
    - D.S. Dye Exhibit papers (Box 17, Folder 197)
    - Newspaper clippings re. Dyes (Box 17, Folder 198)
    - "ChinaThe Early Years", collected letters of Dyes (Box 17, Folder 199)
    - DSD's notebooks (Box 17, Folder 200)
    - DSD, notes on Sermon on the Mount (Box 18, Folder 201)
    - Chinese maps (Box 18, Folder 202)
    - Pictures of DSD and JBD (Box 18, Folder 203)
    - Photos of missionaries and/or home friends (Box 18, Folder 204)
    - Photo of West China Union University (Box 18, Folder 205)
    - Photos: Chinese people with scenery (Box 18, Folder 206)
    - Scenic photographs (Box 18, Folder 207)
    - Photos: Architecture - Buildings and bridges (Box 18, Folder 208)
    - Photos: Painting, sculpture, Chinese dress (Box 18, Folder 209)